Experience replay helps us address one type of correlation.
经验回放可以帮助我们解决一种类型的联系
That is between consecutive experience tuples.
即元组之间的连续经验
There is another kind of correlation that Q-learning is susceptible to.
Q 学习还容易受到一种联系的影响
Q-learning is a form of Temporal Difference or TD learning, right?
Q 学习是一种时间差分 (TD) 学习 对吧
Here, R plus gamma times
这里 R 加上 γ
the maximum possible value from the next state is called the TD target.
乘以下个状态的最大潜在值称为 TD 目标
And our goal is to reduce the difference between
我们的目标是缩小该目标
this target and the currently predicted Q-value.
和当前预测 Q 值之间的差异
This difference is the TD error.
这个差异是 TD 误差
Now, the TD target here is supposed to be
这里的 TD 目标应该取代的是
a replacement for the true value function q pi (S,
真值函数 qπ(S,A)
A) which is unknown to us.
我们不知道真值函数是什么
We originally used q pi to define a squared error loss,
我们一开始使用 qπ 定义平方误差损失
and differentiated that with respect to w to get our gradient descent update rule.
并针对 w 差分化 以便获得梯度下降更新规则
Now, q pi is not dependent on our function approximation or its parameters,
qπ 并不依赖于我们的函数逼近器或其参数
thus resulting in a simple derivative, an update rule.
因此形成一个简单的导数 即更新规则
But, our TD target is dependent on these parameters which means simply
但是 TD 目标依赖于这些参数
replacing the true value function q pi with
因此直接将真值函数 qπ 替换成这样的目标
a target like this is mathematically incorrect.
在数学上不成立
We can get away with it in practice because
在现实中 可以忽略该问题
every update results in a small change to the parameters.
因为每个更新都会使参数出现小小的变化
We're just generally in the right direction.
我们基本上是朝着正确的方向前进
If we set alpha equals one and leap towards the target then we'd likely overshoot,
如果将 α 设为 1 并跳转到目标 那么可能会越过目标
and land in the wrong place.
并进入错误的区域
Also, this is less of a concern when we use a lookup table or
此外 如果我们使用查询表或字典 则不是什么大问题
a dictionary since Q-values are stored separately for each state action pair.
因为每个状态动作对的 Q 值会单独存储
But, it can affect learning significantly when we use function approximation,
但是当我们使用函数逼近时 会显著影响到学习效果
where all the Q-values are intrinsically tied together through the function parameters.
因为所有 Q 值都通过函数参数固有地联系到一起
You may be thinking, "Doesn't experience replay take care of this problem?"
你可能会问“经验回放不会解决该问题吗？”
Well, it addresses a similar but slightly different issue.
它解决的是有点相似 但是稍微不同的问题
There we broke the correlation effects between
对于经验回放 我们通过不按顺序随机地取样元组
consecutive experience tuples by sampling them randomly out of order.
打破了连续经验元组之间的联系
Here, the correlation is between the target and the parameters we are changing.
这里的问题是 目标和我们要更改的参数之间有联系
This is like chasing a moving target, literally.
这就像追赶一个移动的目标
In fact, it's worse.
实际上 更糟糕
It's like trying to train a donkey to walk
就像骑在驴背上训练驴沿直线行走
straight by sitting on it and dangling a carrot in front.
但是杆子上的胡萝卜会随之摆动
Yes, the donkey might step forward and the carriage
没错 驴子可能会向前行走
usually gets further away always staying a little out of reach.
胡萝卜通常都被甩到前方 使驴子够不着
But, contrary to popular belief,
但是和常识相反
this doesn't quite work as you would expect.
实际效果并不是你想象的那样
The carrot is much more likely to bounce around
胡萝卜更有可能四处随机甩动
randomly throwing the donkey off with every jerky
使驴子每一步走起来都很不平稳
step each action affects the next position of
并以不可预测的复杂形式
the target in a very complicated and unpredictable manner.
影响到下个目标位置
You shouldn't be surprised if the donkey gets
驴子很有可能会到处跳动
frustrated jumping around the spot and gives up.
最终放弃行走
Instead, you should get off the donkey
你应该从驴背上下来
stand in one place and dangle the carrot from there.
站在一个位置并用杆子摆动胡萝卜
Once the donkey reaches that spot,
当驴子抵达该位置后
move a few steps ahead,
再向前移动几步
dangle another carrot and repeat.
重新用杆子摆动胡萝卜并重复这一流程
What you're essentially doing is decoupling the target's position from
这样做本质上是将目标位置与驴子的动作拆分开来
the donkey's actions giving it a more stable learning environment.
为驴子提供一个更加稳定的学习环境
We can do pretty much the same thing in Q-learning by
我们也可以在 Q 学习中进行几乎一样的操作
fixing the function parameters used to generate our target.
将用于生成目标的函数参数固定起来
The fixed parameters indicated by a w minus are
用 w- 表示的固定参数
basically a copy of w that we don't change during the learning step.
本质上是在学习过程中不会更改的 w 副本
In practice, we copied w into w minus,
在现实中 我们将 w 替换为 w-
use it to generate targets while changing w for a certain number of learning steps.
用它来生成目标和更改 w 并持续一定数量的学习步骤
Then, we update w minus with the latest w,
然后使用最新的 w 更新 w-
again, learn for a number of steps and so on.
再次学习一定数量的步骤 以此类推
This decouples the target from the parameters,
这样可以使目标和参数拆分开来
makes the learning algorithm much more stable,
使学习算法更加稳定
and less likely to diverge or fall into oscillations.
并且不太可能会发散或振荡